American Vaudeville Museum collection, 1850s-2007 (bulk 1910s-1940s)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series XIV: Kill Kare Kouple Collection, ca. 1890-1933, .25 linear foot
  There is also correspondence, a biographical sketch, a list of songs composed by the couple, and an excerpt from a draft of a biography, "Back Drop: A Vaudeville Love Story", all written by their daughter, Nancy (Hennings) Tomlin, who contributed these materials to the American Vaudeville Museum.
  John Hennings (1886-1933) began performing as a young child with his father, John Bernard Hennings, and his sister Mamie; they were known as the Hennings Trio. His mother had performed with her sister as the Lee Sisters; his cousin Bessie McCoy was also an entertainer, the "Yama-Yama girl." As a young man John performed in vaudeville acts with his sister and her husband.
  Winnie Hamlet (1882-1961) was the daughter of Mary Baker Hamlet and Charles Hamlet. Her mother was a talented instrumentalist who studied with Sam Pryor, a military band leader in St. Joseph, Missouri, where Winnie was born. The family played locally as the Hamlet Family Band, with Winnie on cornet. At sixteen Winnie joined The Navassar Ladies Band as a cornet player, and toured with them for nine years. An offshoot of this group played in vaudeville theaters, and Winnie joined them. She met John Hennings in a vaudeville theater, and they were married in 1908.
  John and Winnie named themselves the Kill Kare Kouple and developed a popular act that included his trombone, piano and dancing, her cornet and songs, and comic banter. He capitalized on his slender build in a humorous manner that lent him the nickname "The Grasshopper Dancer." In 1913 they toured with the Sarah Bernhardt tour as the top vaudeville act. In 1915 they traveled to London where John performed in a show at the London Hippodrome, "Push and Go!" With the flare-up of war, they performed in hospitals and elsewhere; John also entertained troops in France and Belgium. It is possible that he was affected by poison gas at Ypres, since he suffered chronically from pneumonia after that. They returned to the U.S. and continued to perform in war benefits, including with Lily Langtry.
  John performed in several musical shows in the early 1920s. Winnie was raising their daughter and missed performing herself, but she contributed a song to John's act in "A Trial Honeymoon" and as a result their infant daughter was included in the act. John then went to Hollywood, and in 1930 he played in his only film, The Poor Millionaire, directed by Richard Talmadge. His health failed and they relocated near extended family in St. Joseph, Missouri, where John died three years later at age forty-seven. Winnie opened a restaurant after that, and died at the age of eighty.
  - Correspondence from Nancy (Hennings) Tomlin (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Biography (3 pages) of John and Winnie Hennings, by Nancy (Hennings) Tomlin (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Excerpt from draft of biography, Back Drop, by Nancy Tomlin (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Papers, miscellaneous (Box 46, Folder 4)
    Thank-you in "Celtic" style handwriting from John F. Loyd (photocopy)
    List of films by Richard Talmadge (photocopy)
  - Mary [Hamlet] - Sam Pryor, Winnie & Navassar Orchestra - pictures (digital and photocopy) (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - John Hennings - pictures (digital and photocopy) (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - John and Winnie Hennings - pictures (digital and photocopy) (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Press clipping photocopies: Sarah Bernhardt [in "Phedre"], New York, 1913 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Press clipping photocopies: "Push and Go!", London, 1915 (Box 46, Folder 9)
  - Press clipping photocopies: "Take It From Me", 1923 (Box 46, Folder 10)
  - Press clipping photocopies: "A Trial Honeymoon", 1924 (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - Press clipping photocopies: "Dutch Girl", Hollywood, 1925 (Box 46, Folder 12)
  - Press notices (Box 46, Folder 13)
  - Press notices (duplicates) (Box 46, Folder 14)
- Series XV: Olsen and Johnson Collection, ca. 1941-1949, 1995-2002, .15 linear foot
  This collection contains material related to the career of Ole Olsen and Chic Johnson. It includes signed photographs, playbills, posters and sheet music from Hellzapoppin. It also includes correspondence between Frank Cullen and the daughter of Ole Olsen, Moya Olsen Lear, and his grandson, Stephen Ron Olsen.
  Ole Olsen (born John Sigvard Olsen, 1892-1963) and Chic Johnson (born Harold Ogden Johnson, 1891-1962) were originally musical entertainers from the Midwest (Indiana and Illinois) where they met and worked together as band mates. From there they began performing as a vaudeville comedy act. Their revue "Hellzapoppin" became a great success on Broadway in 1938 and a motion picture in 1941. Their comedy act did not translate well or successfully in the Hollywood film setting; they did some television in 1949 and continued to perform in their own revues during the early 1950s in Las Vegas, where they eventually retired.
  - Correspondence (Box 47, Folder 1)
    Letters from Moya Olsen Lear to Frank Cullen, 1995-1999
    E-mail from Stephen Ron Olsen to Frank Cullen, 2002
  - Articles (Box 47, Folder 2)
    The Milwaukee Journal - Screen and Radio, Sunday, July 23, 1944 (color original and photocopy)
    "Olsen & Johnson, the zaniest of the zanies" by Charles Stumpf, Classic Images website, accessed Dec. 15, 1999
  - Publicity photographs, 1943, Postcard, "Chic Johnson in Sons of Fun", 1941, photo by W. Eugene Smith (2 copies) (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Programs and sheet music (Box 47, Folder 4)
    The Playbill for the Winter Garden (New York)
    "Hellzapoppin", beginning Monday, July 21, 1941
    "Sons O' Fun", beginning Sunday, December 28, 1941
    "Laffing Room Only", beginning Sunday, June 24, 1945
    Chicago Stage, 1945 (photocopy)
    "Laffing Room Only" (souvenir flyer)
    "Olsen & Johnson's Sons o' Fun", souvenir program, ca. 1943
    "Olsen & Johnson in Laffing Room Only", souvenir program, ca. 1944
    "Olsen and Johnson's New Hellzapoppin of 1940", souvenir program
    "G'Bye Now, Olsen and Johnson's New Hellzapoppin of 1941", sheet music
    "Souvenir program, Olsen and Johnson in Funzapoppin", ca. 1949
  - Olsen & Johnson perpetual calendar, signed by Moya Olsen Lear, ca. 1999 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - "Hellzapoppin'" (modern reproduction of poster, for 1941 motion picture), Note: stored in Box 23, Posters and Oversize Items
- Series XVI: Sonia Serova Collection, ca. 1917-1925, .1 linear foot
  This series comprises five items related to modern dance, most including musical scores.
  Sonia Serova trained in dance at the Wordsworth School in London, and was influenced by ancient Greek sports and vase paintings, as a disciplined approach that countered the then-popular trend for "aesthetic" dancing. Her style of modern dance was known as "nature dancing." She directed the Vestoff-Serova Russian School of Dancing in New York City, along with her husband, Veronine Vestoff,, who studied ballet at the Russian Imperial Academy of Arts in Moscow. A film, Sonia Serova Dancers, was produced in 1924.
  - Dance program, 1922-23, Dance of the Witches: group dance for 6 babies, dance arr. by Sonia Serova, undated; Dance of the Witches (reference photocopy) (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Publications (Box 47, Folder 7)
    Baby Work by Sonia Serova, undated (after 1917)
    Nature Dancing: a text-book to perfect natural movement (cover subtitle: The poetry of motion) by Sonia Serova, undated (after 1916)
    Talented Tots by Sonia Serova, 1925
- Series XVII: Doreen Rae Collection, ca. 1919-1931, .25 linear foot
  This series comprises photographs and two scrapbooks, documenting the career of Pearl (Dorothy Elizabeth) Hoff (1912-2003), whose stage name was Doreen Rae. The scrapbooks contain mostly newspaper clippings, with some photographs and other texts. There are loose photographs and a few clippings, many of them apparently removed from another scrapbook. There is a short biographical sketch written by her daughter, Carolyn Mooney, who contributed these materials. (Note: This collection was originally received organized as part of the Performers files.)
  Pearl Hoff's family came to Long Beach from Toronto. She first performed at age five as "Lil" Miss Long Beach. By age seven she was performing on the Pantages circuit and at Chautauqua shows, in Canada as well as the U.S., with her mother's support. She toured with vaudeville shows along with two other girls who were friends of hers, Patty Kinney and Fredlyn (also spelled Fredlin, Fredline, Fredaline) Singleton. She was part of the Franchon & Marco group, which featured the singer Rose Valyda, and sang and danced as leading soloist in their act "Baby Songs" during a year-long tour. Aida Broadbent, who was then director for Franchon and Marco, gave Pearl dance lessons. Her older sister, Greta (Gretna?) Murray, also performed in a vaudeville comedy act, with her husband Billy Murray, and they ran the Oriental Theater in North Long Beach; she died at age twenty-six. Her brother Gordon died of tuberculosis at age 19, when Pearl was 12.
  Around 1930 Pearl took on the stage name Doreen Rae. She was still associated with Fanchon & Marco, along with a ukulele playing comedian named Bob (Uke) Henshaw, the trapeze artists Ed and Jennie Rooney, The Four O'Connors, and the Allison Troupe (from Berlin), in a 1931 touring show called "Vaudeville Echoes."
  Around 1935, at age twenty-three, Pearl stopped touring; she married Robert Leland Mooney and had three children. She continued to perform in the Long Beach area. After her husband's death in the late 1940s she worked at Pacific Press in Los Angeles.
  - Biography (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Clippings (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 1 - Pearl Hoff, ca. 1919-1930 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 2 - Doreen Rae, ca. 1930-1931 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 1 (reference photocopy) (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 2 (reference photocopy) (Box 48, Folder 7)
- Series XVIII: Gondoliers-Ricci Collection, 1933-1936, 1.25 linear feet
  This collection comprises papers, photographs, and a scrapbook, documenting the career of Nick Ricci and his musical group in the mid-1930s. There are contracts and business correspondence, a receipt for membership in the Chicago Federation of Musicians in 1936, and a handwritten log of income. The photographs are mostly promotional portraits of the group; there are also some stage shots of them as part of a larger ensemble, including their performance with the Chef Milani show. There is a large poster (3-1/2 by 2-1/3 feet) for the "Skipper" Don Mills show featuring the Four Gondoliers as well as "Blib and Blob" and others, from April 1934, which was originally stored folded in the scrapbook. The collection also includes Nick Ricci's violin. These materials were donated to the American Vaudeville Museum by his sons, Larry Ricci, Paul Ricci and Henry Ricci.
  Nick Ricci was part of a Seattle musical group known originally as the Four Gondoliers and later the Three Gondoliers, or simply the Gondoliers. Two other members were Henry Ricci and Al Maletta (b.1914). Nick played violin, and the others played accordion and clarinet / saxophone. A fourth member, Henry Maiorano, also played accordion, but left the group sometime in 1934. Their nicknames were Icky, Wicky, Wacky and Woo. They were still in high school when they began performing.
  Their first performance that is documented in this collection is the Black Ball Line and Egyptian Theatre radio and stage contest in Seattle, in August 1933. As winners of a McKesson opportunity contest, the Four Gondoliers played in vaudeville acts with Skipper Don Mills, of Portland, around Oregon, northern California, and Washington in early 1934. The act was called Don Mills and His Wonder Stars, and included a dozen other performers. By mid-1934 they were performing with Chef (Joe) Milani's cooking musicale show, in venues including Oakland and Los Angeles. By 1936 they called themselves the Three Ritto Brothers, and were touring the Bert Levey Circuit of Vaudeville Theatres. They also used the name The Three Italian Street Singers.
  Information about Nick Ricci's later life is not provided. Al Maletta later moved to Yakima and started an accordion studio, according to information from the Yakima Valley Museum.
  - Papers, 1933-1936 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1933-1936 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1933-1936 (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook (reference copy) (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Poster, 1934 (Box Oversize)
  - Violin in case with two bows, extra parts (bridge, strings, rosin, etc.) (Box 50)
- Series XIX: Rooney Collection, ca. 1892-2006, bulk ca. 1910-1940s, 3.5 linear feet
  This series consists of materials relating to Julia Rooney (Clinton) (1887-1990), and to a lesser degree to her brother Pat Rooney Sr. (II) (1880-1962), and his son Pat Rooney Jr. (III, or Clarence Patrick Rooney) (1909-1979). There are numerous photographs, mostly autographed publicity photos of entertainers and actors, which were given to the youngest Pat Rooney and his wife, Estelle (Wright) Rooney, and displayed in their beach front restaurant, The Dog House, on Lake Blaisdell, a New Hampshire summer vaudeville colony. There is a short family history written by Estelle Rooney; as well as clippings about Chester (Chet) Wright. Some family photographs are included, as well as two late 19th century cabinet cards of entertainers, and a silhouette cut-out apparently of Walter Clinton.
  Julia Rooney's materials include a scrapbook containing clippings about her early career with her sister Josie; her solo career from 1910 to the teens; and her duo career with Walter Clinton (1890-1966), whom she married in 1915. Julia Rooney's other sibling performers, Mattie Rooney (Kennedy) (1878-1950), and Pat Sr., are mentioned in the scrapbook clippings. Her papers include the passenger list from the Lusitania from the voyage that she and Josie took upon their return from their first European tour in June 1908, as well as copyright documents, awards and recognitions. Performance programs are included in the scrapbook and printed matter. The collection includes a few items of memorabilia, such as an honorary plaque to Walter Clinton from the Hollywood Comedy Club (1949-1961) and a trophy to Julia Rooney from the Ladies' Comedy Club (1972).
  Most of the loose clippings, documents, performance programs and other printed matter, and a few of the photographs, relating to Julia Rooney and her family were received stored loose within the scrapbook. The scrapbook pages were mostly detached when received, and include three different page styles and two sets of covers. There is a small autograph-style album containing snapshot photographs, approximately 2-1/4 by 4-1/8 inches, of theaters, many with "Clinton & Rooney" visible on the marquee, and some with locations noted. There are some photographs of Pat Rooney, Sr.
  Pat Rooney Sr. and Julia Rooney were two of the children of the original Pat Rooney (1884-1892), a boxer who became famous as a performer, especially for clog dance. Julia Rooney and her siblings began performing as children in the 1890s. Julia and her sister Josie toured as the Rooney Sisters (1903-1910), "daughters of Pat Rooney"; their act split up when Josie married during their second European tour. In the teens Julia became known as "The Girl with the Million Dollar Legs." Julia and the singer and actor Walter Clinton (1890-1966), who performed together as Clinton & Rooney, married on Christmas Day 1915. In the 1920s they toured with an accompanying ten-piece band. With the end of the vaudeville era around 1930 they relocated to Hollywood, where Julia opened a dance school. She performed in Ken Murray's Blackouts from 1942 to 1949, and appeared on television in The Sun City Scandals at the age of 82.
  Pat Rooney Jr. was the son of Julia’s brother, Pat Sr., a well-known vaudeville and Broadway dancer, and his first wife, the dancer Marion Bent. (Over the decades, the billing names of the male Rooneys changed. Pat Rooney referred originally to the grandfather, Pat Jr. to his son, and Pat III to the grandson. Sometime in the 1930s, after the public memory faded of the original Pat Rooney, his son, Pat II, simply dropped the “Jr.” from his billing and became Pat Rooney, while his son, Pat III, took the name Par Rooney Jr. The Pat Rooneys (ii and III) performed together in the 1930s in a father/son dance act. Pat (II)’s last notable engagement was a featured role in the cast of the original production of Guys and Dolls, 1950-53. Pat III largely retired from dance by 1940; he married Estelle Wright (1916-2006), whose parents, Chester A. Wright and Ola Gay Wright, were traveling wagon-show entertainers. Chet’s acts included trained dogs and birds, and marionettes. Ola sang, danced, and played mandolin and banjo. Estelle performed with her parents on the vaudeville circuit as a child. Pat and Estelle Rooney operated a hot dog stand called The Dog House in Lake Blaisdell, New Hampshire, an area that served as a summer colony for vaudeville performers, for 32 years; it closed in 1984.
  - Pat and Estelle Rooney collection
    - Papers, miscellaneous, from and concerning Estelle Rooney (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, concerning Chester (Chet) A. Wright (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Typescript - 2 fragments, concerning Chet Wright and Ola Gay Wright (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Photographs and digital prints, of Chet Wright and The Dog House (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, bulk 1940s (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, bulk 1940s (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Photographs, bulk 1940s (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, bulk 1940s (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, bulk 1940s (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - Julia Rooney collection
    - Rooney Sisters chronology, 1903-1910; typed after 1966 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, to Julia Rooney (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Copyright materials (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Documents (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Printed matter (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Printed matter (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Awards and recognitions (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, 1910s-1983 (bulk 1910s-1940s) (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Photocopies and digital image printouts (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1910s-1920s - loose clippings accompanying Julia Rooney scrapbook (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Clippings, 1930s-1980s - loose clippings accompanying Julia Rooney scrapbook (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - Clippings fragments, from Julia Rooney scrapbook (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Julia Rooney scrapbook, part 1 - reference photocopy (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - Julia Rooney scrapbook, part 2 - reference photocopy (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Julia Rooney scrapbook, part 3 - reference photocopy (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - Julia Rooney album of theater photographs - reference photocopy (Box 52, Folder 16)
  - Julia Rooney scrapbook, 1892-1980s (bulk 1906-1920s), Note: Not available for viewing due to fragility; reference photocopy is in Box 52.
    - Julia Rooney scrapbook, part 1 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Julia Rooney scrapbook, part 2 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Julia Rooney scrapbook, part 3 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Julia Rooney album of theatre photographs, ca. 1920s, Note: Not available for viewing due to fragility; reference photocopy is in Box 52. (Box 54)
  - Memorabilia - Julia Rooney and Walter Clinton (Box 55)
    Engraved copper plate, for Julia Rooney business card
    Key chain tab - Ken Murray's "Blackouts", 5th year, El Capitan Theatre
    Plaque for Walter Clinton, honorary life member, Hollywood Comedy Club, 1961
    Trophy for Julia Clinton from Ladies' Comedy Club, 1972
  - Photographs - Pat Rooney, Sr., Note: one photograph is partly adhered to broken glass, must be handled carefully. (Box 56)
- Series XX: Frank J. Sidney Collection, ca. 1900-1965, bulk ca. 1900-1928, .5 linear foot
  This series consists of photographs, negatives, papers, and an ad printing block, documenting the career of Frank J. Sidney. The photographs depict a circus tour in India as The Great Sidneys, a performance troupe tour in Australia in 1908, troupe portraits in Johannesburg in 1913, and some acrobatic acts. Some of the photographs are annotated. From 1922 to 1925 Frank J. Sidney & Co. appeared in B.F. Keith's and other theatres in Brighton Beach, Jersey City, and Philadelphia. His act at that time was called "A Morning in a Sportsman's Garden", and featured "Zillah the Singing Dog."
  The papers are mostly theater programs; there is also a copy of Sidney's handwritten 1965 will. There are postcards sent in 1960 and a 1963 portrait of Sidney. The ad printing plate is mounted on wood with a partial page with printed text adhered, advertising a Labor Day event featuring "Frank Sidney and Abe Clown Cop". The bulk of this collection was originally received as part of the Performers materials.
  - Photographs, ca. 1900-1928 (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, ca. 1900-1928 (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - Photographs and postcards, 1960, 1963 (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - Negatives, ca. 1900, Note: extremely fragile (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Papers, 1922-1925, 1965 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - Ad block printing plate (Box 58)
- Series XXI: Leon Errol Collection, 1904-1940s, 1.25 linear feet
  This collection comprises primarily two scrapbooks describing the stage career of the comedian Leon Errol (1881 or more likely, 1876-1951), on the vaudeville circuits in the Northwest and then in New York with the Ziegfeld Follies. There are also later publicity photographs of Errol from Culver Pictures, First National Pictures, Universal Pictures, and Paramount Pictures, including roles from "Sally", "A Lunatic at Large", "Dancing Co-Ed", and "Princess O'Hara." Miscellaneous papers include correspondence from Chet Dowling that accompanies photocopies about the Ziegfeld Follies and the role of Abe Erlanger as a financial backer for Florenz Ziegfeld, as well as information about Errol's career.
  The first scrapbook consists of newspaper clippings, playbills, programs, and handwritten notes from 1904-1906, documenting the Errol's early career in the Northwest and West Coast as part of the Edward Shields vaudeville company. Its cover has a label for "Gerald and Errol, German Dialect Comedians." There are two pages of handwritten text - one of sailor lyrics, and one of a short stage bit - and a loose sheet of handwritten comedy lines.
  The second scrapbook documents Errol's career on Broadway, including performances in the Ziegfeld Follies of 1911, 1912, 1913, and 1914 along with his wife, Stella Chatelaine. There is a program from August 1910 of their comedy performance "A Complicated Affair" with The New Jersey Lillies; that performance was staged by and largely created by Errol. The bulk of the scrapbook is news clippings. There is also a New York Star cover from October 26, 1912 featuring Errol along with Bert Williams and Ida Adams in a scene from the Ziegfeld Follies; and an undated playbill from The Player for the New Jersey Lilies Co., featuring Leon Errol as principal comedian, Stella Chatelaine as "The Rag Dancer", and others. Leon Errol's time with the Ziegfeld Follies was as a stage director as well as a principal comedian. Errol and Bert Williams (1872-1922) teamed up in four Follies to become the first notable "white and black race" act in mainstream American show business. They wrote the sketches themselves, and Errol portrayed the fumbling master and Williams, the wily servant. It concludes with coverage of his production "Hitchy Koo 1918", sponsored by Raymond Hitchcock, in which he introduced Ray Dooley of vaudeville's "tumbling Dooleys" to Broadway.
  The scrapbooks were donated to the American Vaudeville Museum by Dale Jones and Valerie Speaks of Long Beach in 2004. The other materials are from a variety of sources.